I'm going to talk to you tonight
سوف أتحدث معكم الليلة
about coming out of the closet,
عن الخروج للعلن،
and not in the traditional sense,
وليس كما هو معتاد سماعه،
not just the gay closet.
ليس بخصوص المثلية الجنسية.
I think we all have closets.
إني أعتقد أننا جميعنا لدينا أسرار.
Your closet may be telling someone
قد يكون سرك هو إخبارك لشخص
you love her for the first time,
أنك تحبه لأول مرة،
or telling someone that you're pregnant,
أو إخبار شخص بأنك حامل،
or telling someone you have cancer,
أو إخبار شخص بأنك مصاب بالسرطان،
or any of the other hard conversations
أو بدء أي محادثة صعبة أخرى
we have throughout our lives.
قد نمر بها خلال حياتنا.
All a closet is is a hard conversation,
كل حديث عن سر، هو حديث صعب،
and although our topics may vary tremendously,
وعلى الرغم من أن مواضيعنا قد تختلف كثيرًا،
the experience of being in
إلّا أن تجربة أن تعيش
and coming out of the closet is universal.
والتحرر من الانغلاق هي تجربة عالمية.
It is scary, and we hate it, and it needs to be done.
إنّه أمر مخيف ونكرهه، لكن يجب القيام به.
Several years ago,
منذ بعض سنوات مضت،
I was working at the South Side Walnut Cafe,
كنت أعمل في مقهى ساوث سايد والنات.
a local diner in town,
وهو مطعم محليّ في المدينة،
and during my time there I would go through phases
وأثناء عملي، كنت أمرّ بفترات
of militant lesbian intensity:
نضال شديد للمثليّة الأنثوية:
not shaving my armpits,
كعدم حلاقة إبطيّ
quoting Ani DiFranco lyrics as gospel.
الاقتباس من أغاني 'أني دي فرنكو' كتراتيل.
And depending on the bagginess of my cargo shorts
واعتمادا على التهدل في سراويل 'كارجو' القصيرة الخاصة بي
and how recently I had shaved my head,
وكيف مؤخرا كنت قد حلقت رأسي،
the question would often be sprung on me,
فإن السؤال غالبا ما يكون انتشر عني،
usually by a little kid:
عادة من قبل طفل صغير:
"Um, are you a boy or are you a girl?"
"هم، هل أنت صبي أو فتاة؟"
And there would be an awkward silence at the table.
وسيكون هناك صمت محرج على الطاولة.
I'd clench my jaw a little tighter,
فأكشر فكي أكثر تشددا قليلا،
hold my coffee pot with a little more vengeance.
أحمل وعاء القهوة بانتقام أكثر قليلا.
The dad would awkwardly shuffle his newspaper
يقوم الأب بتحريك ورق صحيفته بشكل مربك
and the mom would shoot a chilling stare at her kid.
والأم تطلق نظرات إلى طفلها تقشعر لها الأبدان.
But I would say nothing,
ولكن لا أقول شيئا،
and I would seethe inside.
وأبقى مهتاجة داخليا.
And it got to the point where every time I walked up
وصلت إلى نقطة حيث في كل مرة أمشي
to a table that had a kid anywhere between three and 10 years old, I was ready to fight.
إلى طاولة موجود فيها طفل يتراوح عمره بين 3 و10 سنة، كنت على استعداد للقتال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that is a terrible feeling.
وهذا شعور رهيب.
So I promised myself, the next time, I would say something.
لذلك وعدت نفسي، في المرة القادمة، سوف أقول شيئا.
I would have that hard conversation.
وسوف أخوض تلك المناقشة الصعبة.
So within a matter of weeks, it happens again.
إذا، في غضون أسابيع، حدث ذلك مجددا.
"Are you a boy or are you a girl?"
"هل أنت صبي أو فتاة؟"
Familiar silence, but this time I'm ready,
الصمت مألوف، ولكن هذه المرة أنا مستعدة،
and I am about to go all Women's Studies 101
وأنا على وشك أن أرمي جميع مقررات الدراسات النسائية التمهيدية
on this table. (Laughter)
في هذه الطاولة. (ضحك)
I've got my Betty Friedan quotes.
لدي اقتباس لبيتي فريدان.
I've got my Gloria Steinem quotes.
لدي اقتباس لغلوريا ستاينم.
I've even got this little bit from "Vagina Monologues" I'm going to do.
لدي حتى القليل من مقاطع من "Vagina Monologues" لتأديتها.
So I take a deep breath and I look down
لذلك أخذت نفسا عميقا ونظرت إلى أسفل
and staring back at me is a four-year-old girl in a pink dress,
ومن تحدق في وجهي هي فتاة عمرها أربع سنوات في ثوب وردي،
not a challenge to a feminist duel,
ليس تحديا للمبارزة النسوية،
just a kid with a question:
مجرد طفل لديه سؤال:
"Are you a boy or are you a girl?"
"هل أنت صبي أو فتاة؟"
So I take another deep breath,
لذلك أخذت نفسا عميقا آخر،
squat down to next to her, and say,
جلست جاثمة أسفل بجانبها، وقلت:
"Hey, I know it's kind of confusing.
"مهلا، أنا أعلم أنه نوعا ما مربك.
My hair is short like a boy's,
شعري قصير مثل صبي،
and I wear boy's clothes, but I'm a girl,
وأرتدي ملابس صبي، ولكن أنا فتاة،
and you know how sometimes you like to wear a pink dress,
وأنت تعرفين كيف أحيانا ترغبين في ارتداء ثوب وردي،
and sometimes you like to wear your comfy jammies?
وأحيانا ترغبين في ارتداء ملابس النوم المريحة الخاصة بك؟
Well, I'm more of a comfy jammies kind of girl."
حسنا، أنا ذلك النوع من الفتيات اللاتي ترتحن أكثر في ملابس نوم مريحة".
And this kid looks me dead in the eye,
فنظرت إلي الطفلة بإمعان ,
without missing a beat, and says,
دون أي صعوبات تذكر، وقالت:
"My favorite pajamas are purple with fish.
" ملابس نوم المفضلة لدي هي البنفسجية مع الأسماك.
Can I get a pancake, please?"
هل يمكنني الحصول على فطيرة، من فضلك؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that was it. Just, "Oh, okay. You're a girl.
وهكذا كان الأمر.فقط، "أوه، حسنا، أنت فتاة.
How about that pancake?"
ماذا عن تلك الفطيرة؟"
It was the easiest hard conversation
كانت أسهل محادثة صعبة
I have ever had.
قد أتيحت لي في أي وقت مضى.
And why? Because Pancake Girl and I,
ولماذا؟ لأن فتاة الفطيرة وأنا،
we were both real with each other.
كنا على حد سواء حقيقيين مع بعضنا البعض.
So like many of us,
بحيث مثل الكثيرين منا،
I've lived in a few closets in my life, and yeah,
عشت داخل بضع خزانات في حياتي، ونعم،
most often, my walls happened to be rainbow.
في معظم الأحيان، حدث أن جدراني كانت قوس قزح.
But inside, in the dark,
ولكن في الداخل، في الظلام،
you can't tell what color the walls are.
لا تستطيع أن تقول ما لون هذه الجدران.
You just know what it feels like to live in a closet.
كنت فقط تعرف ما تشعر به لدى العيش داخل خزانة.
So really, my closet is no different than yours
لذلك حقا، وخزانة ملابسي لا تختلف عما عندكم
or yours or yours.
أو عندك أو عندك
Sure, I'll give you 100 reasons
بالتأكيد، أنا سأعطيك 100 سبب
why coming out of my closet was harder than coming out of yours,
لماذا كانت تجربتي أصعب من تجاربكم،
but here's the thing: Hard is not relative.
لكن هنا مربط الفرس: كلمة صعب ليست شيئا نسبيا.
Hard is hard.
الصعوبة هي الصعوبة.
Who can tell me that explaining to someone you've just declared bankruptcy
من يستطيع أن يخبرني أن تفسر لشخص أنك أعلنت إفلاسك
is harder than telling someone you just cheated on them?
هو أصعب من إخبار شخص ما أنك قمت للتو بخداعه؟
Who can tell me that his coming out story
من يستطيع إخباري أن قصة اعترافه
is harder than telling your five-year-old you're getting a divorce?
أصعب من إخبار طفلك ذي الخمس سنوات أنك تتجهين نحو الطلاق؟
There is no harder, there is just hard.
ليس هناك شيء أصعب، إنه فقط صعب.
We need to stop ranking our hard against everyone else's hard
نحن بحاجة لأن نوقف معايرة مشاكلنا مع مشاكل الآخرين
to make us feel better or worse about our closets
من أجل أن نخفف من أنفسنا أو نزيدها عبئا حيال مشاكلنا
and just commiserate on the fact that we all have hard.
وأن نرثى على الحقيقة الماثلة أننا جميعا نعاني من الصعوبات.
At some point in our lives, we all live in closets,
في مرحلة ما من حياتنا، كلنا نعيش داخل خزانات،
and they may feel safe,
وهو ما قد يشعرنا بالأمان،
or at least safer than what lies on the other side of that door.
أو على الأقل أكثر أمانًا مما يقبع خلف ذلك الباب.
But I am here to tell you,
لكن أنا هنا لأخبركم،
no matter what your walls are made of,
لا يهم من أي شيء صُنعت جدرانكم،
a closet is no place for a person to live.
الخزانة ليست مكانا ليعيش فيه إنسان.
Thanks. (Applause)
شكرًا. (تصفيق)
Me, I had a ponytail, a strapless dress,
بالنسبة لي، كانت لدي ضفيرة كذيل الحصان، وفستان حمالات
and high-heeled shoes.
وأحذية بكعب عالي.
I was not the militant lesbian
لم أكن تلك المثلية المتشددة
ready to fight any four-year-old that walked into the cafe.
مستعدة لأن أتعارك مع أي طفل في الرابعة يأتي إلى المقهى.
I was frozen by fear, curled up in the corner
كنت متجمدة من الخوف، متكومة عند زاوية
of my pitch-black closet
حجرتي حالكة السواد
clutching my gay grenade,
ممسكة بقنبلة المثلية الجنسية،
and moving one muscle is the scariest thing
وكان الإقدام على أي حركة هو أكثر الأشياء رعبًا
I have ever done.
قد أفعلها على الاطلاق
My family, my friends, complete strangers --
عائلتي وأصدقائي والغرباء -
I had spent my entire life
قضيت جل حياتي
trying to not disappoint these people,
في محاولة إرضائهم وعدم تخييب ظنهم،
and now I was turning the world upside down
أما الآن فأنا أقلب الأمور رأسا على عقب
on purpose.
عمدًا.
I was burning the pages of the script
أنا كنت أحرق صفحات السيناريو
we had all followed for so long,
التي طالما اقتفينا أثرها ولزمن طويل،
but if you do not throw that grenade, it will kill you.
لذلك إن لم تلقوا بعيدا بتلك القنبلة، فإنها ستقضي عليكم.
One of my most memorable grenade tosses
واحدة من أكثر الذكريات الحية التي ألقيت فيها القنابل
was at my sister's wedding.
كان في حفل زواج أختي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was the first time that many in attendance
كانت تلك المرة الأولى بحضور عدد كبير
knew I was gay, so in doing my maid of honor duties,
أن يعرفوا أنني مثلية، وخلال قيامي بواجب الضيافة،
in my black dress and heels,
في ثوبي الأسود وكعبي العالي،
I walked around to tables
كنت أتجول بين الطاولات
and finally landed on a table of my parents' friends,
ثم توقفت بطاولة كان يجلس عليها أصدقاء والدي،
folks that had known me for years.
أناس يعرفونني منذ سنيين.
And after a little small talk, one of the women shouted out,
وبعد حديث قصير، صرخت إحدى النساء
"I love Nathan Lane!"
"أنا أحب ناثان لين!"
And the battle of gay relatability had begun.
ثم بدأت حرب مقارنة المثلية الجنسية.
"Ash, have you ever been to the Castro?"
"أش، هل ذهبتي إلى كاسترو من قبل؟"
"Well, yeah, actually, we have friends in San Francisco."
"حسنا، نعم، في الواقع، لنا أصدقاء في سان فرانسيسكو."
"Well, we've never been there but we've heard it's fabulous."
"حسنا، لم نذهب إلى هنالك من قبل ولكن سمعنا أنها مذهلة."
"Ash, do you know my hairdresser Antonio?
"أش، هل تعرفين أنتونيو مصفف شعري؟
He's really good and he has never talked about a girlfriend."
إنه حقا شخص جيد ولم يتحدث مطلقًا عن صديقته."
"Ash, what's your favorite TV show?
"أش، ما هو برنامجك التلفزيوني المفضل؟
Our favorite TV show? Favorite: Will &amp; Grace.
برنامجنا المفضل؟ المفضل: ويل وغراس.
And you know who we love? Jack.
وهل تعلمين من نحب؟ جاك.
Jack is our favorite."
جاك هو المفضل بالنسبة لنا."
And then one woman, stumped
ثم إحدى النساء، مرتبكة
but wanting so desperately to show her support,
لكن أرادت بشدة أن تظهر دعمها،
to let me know she was on my side,
لتلفت نظري أنها تقف في صفي،
she finally blurted out,
في آخر الأمر قالتها ومن غير تفكير،
"Well, sometimes my husband wears pink shirts."
"حسنا، أحيانا زوجي يرتدي قمصانا وردية".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I had a choice in that moment,
وكان عندي الخيار في تلك اللحظة،
as all grenade throwers do.
باعتبار أن الجميع كانوا يلقون قنابلهم.
I could go back to my girlfriend and my gay-loving table
أن باستطاعتي العودة إلى صديقتي وإلى طاولة المثلية المحببة لدي
and mock their responses,
وأن أستهزئ برددوهم،
chastise their unworldliness and their inability
أعاقبهم على سذاجتهم وعجزهم
to jump through the politically correct gay hoops I had brought with me,
من خلال القفز عبر أطواق المثلية الجنسية التي جلبتها معي،
or I could empathize with them
أو أن أستطيع التعاطف معهم
and realize that that was maybe one of the hardest things they had ever done,
وأن ألاحظ أن ذلك ربما كان من أصعب الأشياء التي قاموا بها،
that starting and having that conversation
ذلك البدء بخوض ذلك النقاش
was them coming out of their closets.
كان بمثابة الخروج من خزاناتهم المغلقة.
Sure, it would have been easy to point out where they felt short.
بكل تأكيد، كان من السهولة بمكان أن أشير الى شعورهم بالنقص.
It's a lot harder to meet them where they are
فهم موقفهم أكثر صعوبة بكثير
and acknowledge the fact that they were trying.
والاعتراف بحقيقة أنهم كانوا يحاولون.
And what else can you ask someone to do but try?
وما الذي يُمكن أن تنصح به شخصًا ما غير أن يحاول؟
If you're going to be real with someone,
إذا كنت تهدف إلي الصراحة مع شخص ما،
you gotta be ready for real in return.
فلا بد أن تكون مستعدا للصراحة في المقابل.
So hard conversations are still not my strong suit.
لذا ما زالت الحوارات الحادة ليست نقطة قوتي.
Ask anybody I have ever dated.
إسألوا أي شخص واعدته.
But I'm getting better, and I follow what I like to call
ولكني أتحسن، وأتبع ما أحب أدعوه
the three Pancake Girl principles.
فطيرة المبادىء الثلاث للفتاة.
Now, please view this through gay-colored lenses,
الأن، رجاء انظروا الى الأمر من خلال منظور شخص مثلي،
but know what it takes to come out of any closet
ولكن هل تعرف ما يتطلبه الأمر للخروج للعلن
is essentially the same.
بشكل أساسي هو نفس الشيء.
Number one: Be authentic.
رقم واحد: كن أصليًا.
Take the armor off. Be yourself.
اخلع الدرع. كن نفسك.
That kid in the cafe had no armor,
الطفل عند المقهى لم يكن يحمل درعا،
but I was ready for battle.
ولكني كنت مستعدة للمعركة.
If you want someone to be real with you,
إذا كنت تريد من أحد ما أن يكون صريحا معك،
they need to know that you bleed too.
فهو بحاجة أن يعرف أنك تنزف أيضًا.
Number two: Be direct. Just say it. Rip the Band-Aid off.
رقم اثنين: كن واضحا. فقط قلها. اكسر الحواجز.
If you know you are gay, just say it.
إذا كنت مثلي الجنس، اعترف بذلك.
If you tell your parents you might be gay,
إذا أخبرت والديك أنك ربما قد تكون مثليًا،
they will hold out hope that this will change.
سيكون لديهم الأمل في أن يتغير ذلك.
Do not give them that sense of false hope.
لا تمنحهم ذلك الإحساس بآمال كاذبة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And number three, and most important --
ورقم ثلاثة، والأهم -
Be unapologetic.
لا تعتذر.
You are speaking your truth.
أنت تُخبر بحقيقتك.
Never apologize for that.
لا تعتذر على ذلك إطلاقا.
And some folks may have gotten hurt along the way,
يمكن أن يتأذى البعض على مدى الطريق،
so sure, apologize for what you've done,
لذلك، اعتذر عن أفعالك،
but never apologize for who you are.
ولكن لا تعتذر مطلقًا عن حقيقتك.
And yeah, some folks may be disappointed,
فعلا، البعض قد يخيب ظنهم فيك،
but that is on them, not on you.
لكن ذلك يخصهم، لا يخصك أنت.
Those are their expectations of who you are, not yours.
هذه هي توقعاتهم الخاصة حولك، ليس توقعاتك أنت.
That is their story, not yours.
تلك قصتهم، ليست قصتك.
The only story that matters
القصة الوحيدة التي تهم حقًا
is the one that you want to write.
هي ما كنت تريد أن تكتبه.
So the next time you find yourself
لذلك المرة القادمة عندما تجد نفسك
in a pitch-black closet clutching your grenade,
في الخزانة حالكت السواد ممسكا بقنبلتك،
know we have all been there before.
اعلم أننا جميعنا مررنا بها من قبل.
And you may feel so very alone, but you are not.
وقد تشعر أنك وحيد جدا، ولكنك لست كذلك.
And we know it's hard but we need you out here,
ونحن نعلم أن ذلك صعب ولكننا نحتاجك هنا،
no matter what your walls are made of,
بغض النظر عما صُنعت منه الجدران،
because I guarantee you there are others
لأنني أضمن لكم أن هنالك آخرين
peering through the keyholes of their closets
يحدقون من خلال ثقوب مفاتيح خزاناتهم
looking for the next brave soul to bust a door open, so be that person
يتطلعون إلى الروح الشجاعة لتفتح الباب، لذا كن ذلك الشخص
and show the world that we are bigger than our closets
وأظهر للعالم أننا أكبر من خزاناتنا
and that a closet is no place for a person
وأن تلك الخزانة ليست بمكان يناس شخصا
to truly live.
ليعيش فيه بصدق.
Thank you, Boulder. Enjoy your night. (Applause)
شكرا لكم، بولدر. استمتعوا بأمسيتكم. (تصفيق)